A Guide to the Papers of James Edward Grimsley ca.1957-1997
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of James Edward Grimsely ca. 1957-1997
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9379-a
The papers of J. Edward Grimsley (1927- ), of Henrico County, Virginia, ca. 1957-1997, consist of ca. 4,000 items (15 Hollinger boxes, ca. 6 linear shelf feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the University of Virginia Library in September 2001 by J. Edward Grimsley, Richmond, Virginia.
Biographical/Historical Information
Grimsley was born on May 25, 1927, in Buchanan, Virginia, to James Lowry and Almeda (Thomas) Grimsley. He earned his B.A. degree in Government at the College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia, in 1951 and married Ann Marriott Neblett the same year. He started his new career as a reporter for United Press International, 1951-1952, and served as press relations director for William and Mary, 1952-1953. He has also served on the college's Board of Visitors, beginning in 1990.
Grimsley joined the Richmond Times-Dispatch as a reporter covering state and local politics and urban affairs in 1953. For many years his satirical column "Metronome" also appeared in the Richmond Times-Dispatch, and a collection of these columns was published in Coming Through Awry (1967). He was the editorial page editor of Richmond Times-Dispatch from 1970-1992, becoming chairman of the Editorial Board, 1992-1995. Grimsley was a member of the American Society of Newspaper Editors, the National Conference of Editorial Writers, the Society of Professional Journalists, and Sigma Delta Chi. He was also a member of the adjunct journalism faculty of Virginia Commonwealth University for about twenty years.
Scope and Content
The papers of J. Edward Grimsley (1927- ), of Henrico County, Virginia, ca. 1957-1997, ca. 4,000 items (15 Hollinger boxes, ca. 6 linear shelf feet) consist of editorial correspondence, news clippings, subject files, pamphlets and ephemeral publications from Grimsley's tenure as columnist, editorial page editor, and chairman of the editorial pages of the Richmond Times- Dispatch.
Arrangement
The papers of Edward Grimsley are arranged chiefly in reverse chronological order in three series: I: Correspondence (Boxes 1-8); II: Editorials (grouped by year only in Boxes 9-12) and III: Subject Files (Boxes 12-15 ).
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence (Box 1-8)
  Chiefly reverse chronological order
  - Correspondence: A through E 1967-1992, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: F through Mc 1960-1992, 8 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: M 1978-1991 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: M 1970-1977, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: N through R 1969-1985, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: S 1970-1971 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: T through Z 1970-1995, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Appreciation, Letters of 1978-1980 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Chairman of the Editorial Board 1992-1994 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Congratulations concerning Editorials, etc. 1970-1982, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Contests 1978-1979 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: "Crosscurrents" Column 1988-1992, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Editorials 1968-1979, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Editorials 1980-1991, 9 folders (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Editorials 1992-1997, n.d., 7 folders (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Forum Club 1970-1974 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Invitations - Acceptances 1970-1994, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Invitations - Regrets 1970-1987, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: "Metronome" Column 1967-1971 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Personal 1970-1996, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Politicians 1969-1995, 2 folders, some copies (Box 8)
    these include: Spiro T. Agnew, George Allen, Senator William L. Armstrong, Gerald L. Baliles, Representative Thomas J. Bliley, Jr., Pat Buchanan, George H.W. Bush, Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Jimmy Carter, John N. Dalton, Mills E. Godwin, Jr., Senator Phil Gramm, Justice Albertis S. Harrison, Jr., Delegate Elise B. Heinz, Linwood Holton, Henry E. Howell, Jr., Richard Nixon, Justice Lewis F. Powell, Jr., Dan Quayle, J. Sergeant Reynolds, Charles S. Robb, William B. Spong, Jr., Paul S. Trible, Jr., and Delegate Vivian E. Watts
- Series II: Editorials (Box 9-12)
  Grouped by year only
  - Editorials 1961-1990, 14 folders (Box 9)
  - Editorials 1991-1997, n.d., 5 folders (Box 10)
  - Editorial: "Metronome" Column 1969-1974, n.d., Typescripts (3 folders) (Box 10)
  - Editorials: "Metronome" Column n.d., Typescripts (4 folders) (Box 11)
  - Editorials: "Metronome" Column, News clippings, (10 Folders) (Box 11)
  - Editorials: "Metronome" Column, News clippings ca. 1962-1974, (3 Folders) (Box 12)
  - Editorials: Miscellaneous 1983-1997 (Box 12)
- Series III: Subject Files (Box 12-15)
  - A.H. Robins and Dalkon Shield Debate 1986 (Box 12)
  - American Press Institute 1991 (Box 12)
  - Articles by Edward Grimsley 1965-1988 (Box 12)
  - Biographical Information 1985-1997 (Box 12)
  - Book Reviews 1967-1968 (Box 12)
  - Campus Unrest 1962-1970 (Box 12)
  - Center for the Study of the Presidency 1991-1993 (Box 12)
  - Chesapeake Bay Foundation 1991 (Box 12)
  - Crime and Gun Control 1990-1991 (Box 12)
  - "Dear President Reagan" Open Letters 1981 (Box 12)
  - Environment 1971-1990 (Box 12)
  - First Let's Kill All the Humorists 1966-1970 (Box 12)
    Material for Book Published by the Dietz Press, Richmond (1998)
  - First Let's Kill All the Humorists 1966-1970, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - First Let's Kill All the Humorists 1970-1996 (Box 13)
    Material for Book Published by the Dietz Press, Richmond (1998) re Feminism, Quotas, etc.
  - First Let's Kill All the Humorists 1966-1997 (Box 13)
    Material for Book Published by the Dietz Press, Richmond (1998) re Manners and Customs
  - First Let's Kill All the Humorists 1988-1992 (Box 13)
    Material for Book Published by the Dietz Press, Richmond (1998) re Politics and Politicians
  - Hampden-Sydney 1984 (Box 13)
  - Joel W. Harris 1983 (Box 13)
  - The Heritage Lectures 1992 Nov. 5 (Box 13)
  - Governor Linwood Holton 1970-1974 (Box 13)
  - The Hoover Institution 1995 (Box 13)
  - India 1986 (Box 13)
  - Israel 1971-1972, 1983 (Box 13)
    Trip and Articles written by Grimsley
  - Jesse Jackson 1986 (Box 13)
  - Junior League of Richmond 1986-1993 (Box 13)
  - Junior League of Richmond Booklet 1992-1993 (Box 13)
  - Longwood College 1984-1985 (Box 14)
  - Lottery 1987-1992 (Box 14)
  - Meeting at Novosti News Agency with KGB and Ministry of Defense 1989 Jul. 29 (Box 14)
  - Meeting of Henry Howell and Ed Grimsley: Transcript 1977 Oct. 26 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous 1967-1994 (Box 14)
  - "National Conference of Editorial Writers Forum - USSR/USA 1983" 1983 (Box 14)
  - Oman Sultanate 1978 (Box 14)
  - Pulitzer Prize Nominating Jury 1984-1985 (Box 14)
  - Race Relations 1970-1991 (Box 14)
  - School Desegregation 1970-1972, 1974 (Box 14)
  - School Desegregation - Busing 1970-1972 (Box 14)
  - School Desegregation - Carolyn Bradley, et al 1970-1972 (Box 14)
  - School Desegregation Lawsuits in Federal Courts 1970, 2 folders (Box 14)
    Question "Should the state of Virginia intervene?" addressed to Virginia delegates and state senators by the Richmond Times-Dispatch
  - School Desegregation - Virginia 1970-1973 (Box 15)
  - South Africa 1985-1990 (Box 15)
  - Speeches 1990-1992, n.d., 2 folders (Box 15)
  - John Tower Nomination 1989 (Box 15)
  - Uranium 1983-1985 (Box 15)
  - Virginia Assembly 1983 (Box 15)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University 1989-1993 (Box 15)
  - Virginia Military Institute 1990 (Box 15)
  - John Warner 1987-1991 (Box 15)
  - Washington and Lee University 1991 (Box 15)
  - White House 1983-1986 (Box 15)
  - L. Douglas Wilder 1990-1992 (Box 15)
  - William and Mary - Alumni Medallion 1991-1992 (Box 15)